Guide to the Andrew Spencer Turnipseed Papers, 1902-2002 and undated (bulk 1928-1965)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Andrew Spencer Turnipseed papers, 1902-2002 and undated (bulk 1928-1965)
Turnipseed, Andrew Spencer, 1911-2002.
32.7 linear feet Extent: 20,050 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.01316
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. However, original audio materials are closed to use; listening or viewing copies must be made before contents can be accessed. Also, some collection materials may need preservation work before use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Andrew Spencer Turnipseed Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2002.
Biographical Note
Methodist minister in Alabama, Florida, and New York State from 1933 to 1978. Leader of the progressive wing within Alabama's Methodist Church during 1940s and 1950s; noted for involvement in civil and human rights issues.
Collection Overview
Collection consists primarily of manuscripts and research materials related to Turnipseed's writings (1902-1960s), in particular his multivolume, unpublished autobiography I Tried: An Autobiography of Andrew Spencer Turnipseed. The collection documents Turnipseed's ancestry, early life, and roles as a theologian and activist. Includes many folders of personal and professional correspondence (1929-1980s); lectures and sermons (including 13 audio cassettes); course materials; and travel files. In addition, there are subject files on topics such as Methodism; civil rights; race relations and Southern politics; and public education, including higher education for African-Americans in Alabama. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Subject Headings
Turnipseed, Andrew Spencer, 1911-2002; Turnipseed family; African Americans -- Education -- Alabama; African Americans -- Education (Higher) -- Alabama; Civil rights workers -- Alabama; Civil rights movements -- Alabama -- History -- 20th century; Sermons, American -- 20th century; Methodism -- History; Methodist Church -- Sermons -- 20th century; Methodist Church -- United States; Methodist Church -- United States -- Clergy; Methodist Church -- United States -- History -- 20th century; United States -- Race relations -- History -- 20th century; Alabama -- Race relations; Alabama -- History -- 20th century; Audiocassettes; Sermons; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
Description of Collection
- Accession (2002-0301)
  - Contents of Box 1: (Box 1)
    - Loose miscellaneous materials, 1957-2002 (Box 1)
    - Personal and professional correspondence, 1954-1982 (Box 1)
    - Manuscript, I Tried: An Autobiography of Andrew Spencer Turnipseed (Box 1)
  - Contents of Box 2: (Box 2)
    - Manuscript, I Tried (Box 2)
  - Contents of Box 3: (Box 3)
    - Manuscript, I Tried (Box 3)
    - Manuscript, untitled (Box 3)
  - Contents of Box 4: (Box 4)
    - Manuscript, untitled (Box 4)
  - Contents of Box 5: (Box 5)
    - Theology notes (Box 5)
    - Audio tapes (Box 5)
  - Contents of Box 6: (Box 6)
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
    - Audio tapes of sermons and speeches, ca. 1952-1963 (Box 6)
  - Contents of Box 7: (Box 7)
    - Theology notes (Box 7)
    - Course materials, ca. 1936-1937 (Box 7)
  - Contents of Box 8: (Box 8)
    - Course materials, ca. 1936-1937 (Box 8)
  - Contents of Box 9: (Box 9)
    - Autobiographical research materials, 1928-1932 (Box 9)
  - Contents of Box 10: (Box 10)
    - Autobiographical research materials, 1928-1932 (Box 10)
  - Contents of Box 11: (Box 11)
    - Autobiographical research materials, 1928-1932 (Box 11)
    - Loose miscellaeous materials (Box 11)
  - Contents of Box 12: (Box 12)
    - Subject Files
      - Alabama Temperance Alliance (Box 12)
      - Council on Human Relations (Box 12)
      - Southern Regional Council, Inc. (Box 12)
  - Contents of Box 13: (Box 13)
    - Family budget, corresopndence, and church material, 1940-1941 and undated (Box 13)
    - Annual Methodist Church Conference, Panama City, 1940 (Box 13)
    - Methodist Federation for Social Action (Box 13)
    - Invitations, 1954-1959 (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, Panama City (Box 13)
    - Panama City Conference Advocates, 1940-1944 (Box 13)
  - Contents of Box 14: (Box 14)
    - Annual Methodist Church Conference, Panama City, 1940 (Box 14)
    - Mission trips and Holy Land tour, 1962-1964 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, legal papers (deed), notes, and large index sheets, 1940s (Box 14)
  - Contents of Box 15: (Box 15)
    - Travels
      - Racial Imbalance in the Public Schools (Box 15)
    - Professional correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 15)
  - Contents of Box 16: (Box 16)
    - Professional correspondence, ca. 1954-1959 (Box 16)
    - Methodist Federation for Social Action (Box 16)
    - Conferences, speeches (Box 16)
    - Reviews, items about Turnipseed (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous materials (Box 16)
  - Contents of Box 17: (Box 17)
    - Professional correspondence, ca. 1950s (Box 17)
    - Correspondence about scholarships, conference reports, various clippings and print material, and school papers by Turnipseed, circa 1932-1962 (Box 17)
    - Notebook, Classified Sermon Record (Box 17)
    - Autobiographical research material (Box 17)
  - Contents of Box 18: (Box 18)
    - Personal and professional correspondence, ca. 1960s (Box 18)
    - Travel Journal (Box 18)
    - Material concerning the death of Martha Turnipseed Moore, daughter (Box 18)
    - Correspondence from travels (Box 18)
  - Contents of Box 19: (Box 19)
    - Material related to Methodist Federation for Social Action, (3 folders) (Box 19)
    - Telephone and moving (Box 19)
    - Events (Box 19)
    - Autobiographical research material (Box 19)
  - Contents of Box 20: (Box 20)
    - Vol. II, Chap. 8, (3 folders) (Box 20)
    - Autobiographical research material (Box 20)
    - Professional correspondence, Methodist leaders, 1949-1950s (Box 20)
    - Press publications, general, 1947-1952 (Box 20)
    - Cooperation, Boswell Amendment, Town and Country Commission, Montgomery Ministerial Assoc., 1946-1949 (Box 20)
    - Writings and print materials, 1947, 1952 and undated (Box 20)
  - Contents of Box 21: (Box 21)
    - Professional and personal correspondence, 1960s (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous material (Box 21)
    - Church Reports (Box 21)
    - Theology Orientation (Box 21)
    - Editorial corrections [untitled work] (Box 21)
  - Contents of Box 22: (Box 22)
    - Personal and professional correspondence, 1950s-1980s (Box 22)
    - Loose miscellaneous material (Box 22)
  - Contents of Box 23: (Box 23)
    - Correspondence, personal and church-related, 1942-1944, 1961-1975 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 23)
    - Personal correspondence from J.M. Dannelly, ca. 1929-1930 (Box 23)
    - Citizen Advisory and Education Council (Box 23)
    - Speaking engagements, 1959 (Box 23)
    - General interest, Greenville (Box 23)
    - Registered war rations book and various writings, clippings, and bulletins, 1943, 1961, 1971-1980 and undated (Box 23)
  - Contents of Box 24: (Box 24)
    - Cooperation (Box 24)
    - Education files (Box 24)
    - Celestial politics, 1947 (Box 24)
    - Articles and correspondence (Box 24)
    - Pulpit Echoes, newspaper column, 1947 (Box 24)
    - Youngblood, research notes, 1947-1951 (Box 24)
  - Contents of Box 25: (Box 25)
    - Professional correspondence from Clare Purcell, ca. 1958 (Box 25)
    - Education files, (4 folders) (Box 25)
    - Christian Action for World Peace (Box 25)
    - Alabama Temperance Alliance - constitutional correspondence (Box 25)
  - Contents of Box 26: (Box 26)
    - Personal and professional correspondence, ca. 1950s-1960s (Box 26)
    - Pulpit Echoes, 1958 (Box 26)
  - Contents of Box 27: (Box 27)
    - Professional correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 27)
    - Events, conferences, engagements, ca. 1950s-1970s (Box 27)
    - Course materials (Box 27)
    - Methodist Children's Home (Box 27)
  - Contents of Box 28: (Box 28)
    - Children's Home (Box 28)
    - Transition files (Box 28)
  - Contents of Box 29: (Box 29)
    - Professional correspondence (Box 29)
    - Events, engagements (Box 29)
    - White House Task Force (Box 29)
    - Annual report, Hanson Place Central United Methodist Church, 1960s-1970s (Box 29)
    - Medical records/insurance information (Box 29)
    - Correspondence and clippings, 1957-1959, 1994 (Box 29)
  - Contents of Box 30: (Box 30)
    - Hanson Place Central United Methodist Church (Box 30)
    - Transition from St. Paul's to Hanson Place (Box 30)
  - Contents of Box 31: (Box 31)
    - Niagara Falls, 1962-1966, (2 folders) (Box 31)
    - Europe and USSR Trip, 1962 (Box 31)
    - Pulpit Echoes, 1948-1950, (4 folders) (Box 31)
    - Efforts to move from Niagara Falls, 1963-1965, (2 folders) (Box 31)
  - Contents of Box 32: (Box 32)
    - Toppins correspondence, 1961-1973 (Box 32)
    - Research material and notes, Timely Therapy, 1916-1920 (Box 32)
    - Correspondence from C. G. Gomillion, 1987 (Box 32)
  - Contents of Box 33: (Box 33)
    - Sledd Club, 1943-1945 and undated (Box 33)
    - Research material and notes, Timely Therapy (Box 33)
    - Pulpit Echoes, 1948 (Box 33)
  - Contents of Box 34: (Box 34)
    - Research material and notes, Timely Therapy, (4 folders) (Box 34)
    - Draft, Timely Therapy, (4 folders) (Box 34)
  - Contents of Box 35: (Box 35)
    - Draft, Timely Therapy, (11 folders) (Box 35)
  - Contents of Box 36: (Box 36)
    - Survival-Assistance, 1961 (Box 36)
    - Personal and professional correspondence, 1920s-1960s (Box 36)
    - Research material and notes, Timely Therapy (Box 36)
    - Draft, Timely Therapy (Box 36)
    - Mose, 1930 (Box 36)
    - Emory correspondence, 1929-1930 (Box 36)
  - Contents of Box 37: (Box 37)
    - Methodist Federation for Social Action, 1945-1951 and undated (Box 37)
    - A Positive Program for the South, 1948 (Box 37)
    - Pulpit Echoes, 1948-1950 (Box 37)
    - Committee on Higher Education, Negroes, 1949, 1952, (2 folders) (Box 37)
    - Niagara Falls Ministry material, (2 folders) (Box 37)
  - Contents of Box 38: (Box 38)
    - Sermons by J.F. McLeod, undated (Box 38)
    - Personal and professional correspondence, 1960s-1970s (Box 38)
    - Niagara Falls Ministry material, 1961-1968 and undated (Box 38)
    - Material related to Rev. Frank Donnelly, 1960-1963 (Box 38)
  - Contents of Box 39: (Box 39)
    - Personal and professional correspondence, [1960s] (Box 39)
    - Clippings regarding race, politics, violence in the South, 1957-1958 (Box 39)
    - Address book (Box 39)
    - Daily planner, 1967 (Box 39)
    - Centennial Anniversary, St. Paul's Church, Niagara Falls (Box 39)
    - College materials, Marti Turnipseed (daughter), Boston Univ., Christian Century, 1963-1964 (Box 39)
  - Contents of Box 40: (Box 40)
    - Methodist Children's Home, 1950s, (6 folders) (Box 40)
    - Birmingham-Southern lunch counter sit-in, Marti Turnipseed, 1963-1965, (3 folders) (Box 40)
  - Contents of Box 41: (Box 41)
    - Research files and notes, ca. 1920 (Box 41)
    - Manuscript, Timely Therapy (Box 41)
    - Methodist Children's Home (Box 41)
  - Contents of Box 42: (Box 42)
    - Articles on religion, 1921 (Box 42)
    - Research files, ca. 1914-1920 (Box 42)
    - Original chapters, autobiography (Box 42)
  - Contents of Box 43: (Box 43)
    - Autobiographical research material, ca. 1902-1920 (Box 43)
  - Contents of Box 44: (Box 44)
    - Original chapters, autobiography (Box 44)
  - Contents of Box 45: (Box 45)
    - Autobiographical research material (Box 45)
    - Education files (Box 45)
  - Contents of Box 46: (Box 46)
    - Autobiographical research material (Box 46)
    - Church Forces Organized for Good Government (Box 46)
    - Board of Temperance and Social Service, 1951-1954 (Box 46)
    - Michigan Christian Advocate and Citizens Advisory and Educational Council materials, 1943-1953 (Box 46)
  - Contents of Box 47: (Box 47)
    - Professional correspondence, 1947-1954 (Box 47)
    - Cooperation, 1946-1953 (Box 47)
    - Making Methodism Methodist, publications (Box 47)
    - Original chapters, autobiography (Box 47)
  - Contents of Box 48: (Box 48)
    - Professional correspondence with A.E. Barnett, 1945-1954 (Box 48)
    - Research material, untitled manuscript (Box 48)
    - Youngblood (Box 48)
    - Pulpit Echoes, 1952 (Box 48)
    - Methodist Federation for Social Action (Box 48)
    - Commission on World Peace (Box 48)
  - Contents of Box 49: (Box 49)
    - Pulpit Echoes (Box 49)
    - Autobiographical research material (Box 49)
    - Loose miscellaneous material (Box 49)
  - Contents of Box 50: (Box 50)
    - Research material, untitled manuscript (Box 50)
    - Methodist Federation for Social Action (Box 50)
    - History as a Center of Contemporary Theological Orientation (Box 50)
    - Notes, essays on the Gospels and New Testament (Box 50)
  - Contents of Box 51: (Box 51)
    - Loose miscellaneous materials (Box 51)
    - Notes on the Synoptic Gospels (Box 51)
    - A History of the Christian Church, Williston Walker, Manuscript (Box 51)
  - Contents of Box 52: (Box 52)
    - A History of the Christian Church, Williston Walker, manuscript (Box 52)
    - Research material and original chapters, untitled manuscript (Box 52)
  - Contents of Box 53: (Box 53)
    - Research material and original chapters, untitled manuscript (Box 53)
    - Butts, Thomas, Niagara Falls (sermons and correspondence), [1960s] (Box 53)
  - Contents of Box 54: (Box 54)
    - Protestant and Jewish Association for Care of Blind and Infirm Negroes, 1952-1955 and undated (Box 54)
    - Pulpit Echoes, columns and other items, 1947-1948, 1953, (4 folders) (Box 54)
    - Citizens' Advisory and Education Council, 1947-1957 (Box 54)
    - Dexter Avenue Methodist, 1954 (Box 54)
    - Interdenominational Alliance, 1952 and undated (Box 54)
    - Miscellanous writings and correspondence, 1946-1959 (Box 54)
  - Contents of Box 55: (Box 55)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, sermons, writings, and clippings, 1945-1950, (6 folders) (Box 55)